this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software so welcome everyone to software
engineering radio my name is Kim Carter
I'll be your host for today and today
we've got Peter Budaj Peter Budaj is a
computer scientist a cryptography
engineer and vice president of product
development at the end wind encrypted
cloud service treszura peter has an MSC
in Computer Engineering from the
Budapest University of Technology and
science is PhD candidate he's research
paired engineering and performance peter
started his career at treszura where
prior to his current position he has
lead all cryptography related
development efforts as he loved
cryptography engineering welcome to the
show Peter yeah thanks Kim thanks for
having me so a bit of a disclaimer i'll
i also use treszura and I find that
excellent is file storage is encrypted
file storage I've used a few other
products like Dropbox and in SpiderOak
and you found spider 8 to be a little
bit inferior so you decided to move over
to treasure it and it's it's been really
good and so we've had a few shows now on
on a few topics are related to today's
topic so we've had a show on our cloud
security with Scott Piper and myself
that was show number 314 where we
discussed communications between apps
and the cloud and how they're often not
unencrypted and we had a show on network
security with her own Mir that was show
number 302 we had show an application
security with Zane Leakey
that was show number 309 and we had a
show on docker security with Daigo
moniker that was show number 290 where
we touched on Intel software guard
extensions Easter eggs which we'll
discuss a little bit later on so there's
a relevant article from the I Triple E
Computer Society on today's topic
it's called application layer encryption
for cloud today we're going to be
discussing int wind and
so just kind of stuff now with some
basic questions what is in tween
encryption X actually entering the
encryption means that that data is
protected from from the user's device
and when their is originating from all
the way to the cloud service provider
and back to the users device so there's
no point in time and when the data is
accessible to to the network provider to
the cloud service provider or or or
anyone else while it's being transmitted
or stored in the cloud or stored in in
any place in the internet all the way to
the study to the destination so if we
get traditional example for example like
messaging it's a trivial example so when
I send a message from my mobile phone
and that man it reaches my wife for
example the the message is encrypted and
no one is able to see what's inside what
I was telling to my wife yeah yes
especially the conversion of plaintext
or ciphertext and in an in soft text
into Indra
yes actually it usually means that that
the encryption happen happens on the on
the device on the user's device and not
on not on the server service provider
side what do we need in to end
encryption what's go here the goal is to
do retain privacy so so we can be sure
that that no one is able to see our
private information or data not not even
service providers not even internet
providers or or or any malicious parties
out there who might be interested in
not even like nation-states or
governmental agencies these are a hot
topic nowadays so basically yeah this
the point yes I'm just thinking like one
example would be a year would be a
European organisation which stores its
archive data off-site in the USA and in
under the light the terms of the u.s.
Patriot Act are the American authorities
can demand access to all the data
physically stored within their
boundaries yeah in that case for if the
European service provider uses end to
end encryption or its antolín decryption
to their to its users then even if the
even if the American part the American
provider has to give away the data its
will unencrypted like a garbage which
they cannot really use for anything you
so what sort of things we're trying to
patch it with in vein encryption
actually we can protect anything from
from our personal data like photographs
or - or confidential documents to our to
our voice calls text messaging yeah
there are there is no limit on what we
should protect and actually the more the
more part of our of our private data we
protect it's it's the better you also
the least suspicious that locks to
remove actually got something really
important
to communicate yeah actually when when
when you you know when you just encrypt
a little bit of your traffic traffic and
someone just eavesdropping your your
computer your all your communication and
seeing that okay all the all the
communications were not encrypted so far
but now suddenly it starts to be
encrypted no it's getting suspicious
yeah exactly that's been interesting
part they they would like to look into
so the more we encrypt actually the the
battery we have yes sir so who are we
trying to protect it from generally we
would pay the any malicious parties like
hackers or or or yeah hackers who are
trying to make a profit of our private
information on the on the black market
but if we think about b2b senior
scenarios then we should protect our
data from our competitors for example so
if we have a new a new patent pending
for example or a new invention we would
like to keep it secret for our for our
competitors there are a lot of a lot of
risk groups for example like journalists
or non-governmental organizations were
working in in rather dangerous areas and
a lot of times they're actually their
life are depending on whether they're
their whereabout is not not public so
yeah yeah I know someone that actually
works with our children that have been
abducted and yeah it's really important
for her as well now so what are your
thoughts are we on airing back doors for
the authorities but some here are
stopping the attackers from using them
generally I I don't really have good
opinion and backdoors
I don't think backdoors are a good way
to to
achieve what what they are trying to
achieve usually usually back doors are
energy originating from two source one
are just simply mistakes programming
mistakes or or bugs in the code which
can be done later exploited by by
hackers for example and the other source
of backdoors when when someone just
plans an intentional backdoor in the
application to later gain access to to
the to the information the traditional
so we can say that traditionally these
these are planted by by governmental
organizations we could read about
reading the news about the lot of NSA
scandals like IDI
the most famous one is is the one from
with advanced Snowden Edward Snowden
involved and they are they are putting
back doors to in the in the applications
and cryptographic elements and
cryptographic standards to do later have
control over the over the data and be
able to decrypt the encrypted
information my opinion is that these
backdoors cannot remain like secret
forever
not even agencies like that or companies
can can keep can keep secrets forever
they they are not invulnerable to two
similar attacks as well so so when these
backdoors are getting public so it's
known by everyone suddenly any malicious
person will be able to use this backdoor
to get access to the to the information
and and usually at this at this time the
the affected software on the affected
hardware component is is already widely
deployed in the world so there will be
there it will be really hard to to to
find the mitigation against the
backdoors
for our listeners can you explain
symmetric and asymmetric encryption yes
of course
symmetric encryption is is like the
easiest one to to understand it gets its
name because the encryption and the
decryption uses the same secret we like
to call it a key similarly to a padlock
with a key so when you encrypt the data
you get your plaintext message for
example an email and use it a key and
use cleverly designed algorithms that
clever mathematicians all over the world
created and with the key you can encrypt
the message to another document which
looks like complete garbage - - to the
one who does not have a key and then you
can send this encrypted message over any
kind of transport channel and then at
the other end of the channel if someone
knows the key the exact same key then he
or she will be able to decrypt and and
the C and C the email message that you
just encrypted so this is the symmetric
encryption the asymmetric one is is a
bit trickier it involves two keys
actually so if I would like to send a
message to you I would need your public
key I have to know your public key which
then I can use to send and to encrypt a
message and send it to you and only you
will be able to decrypt it but anyone in
the world can create I can create the
message and encrypt it for you only you
will be able to decrypt it and you will
use your so-called private key for
decryption and the point of a symmetric
encryption is that your private key is
secret you keep it to yourself you never
tell it to anyone but from your private
key
can easily calculate the public key and
the public key has the name public
because it can be can't be distributed
anywhere or in any way for example you
can just create a newspaper
advertisement content in your public key
and then anyone can use C and use your
public key to encrypt messages for you
the point that from the public key
it is like impossible to to calculate
the de private key but from the other
way around this it is feasible easily so
the advantage of using a symmetric
encryption of our symmetric encryption
is that I don't have to meet you I don't
have to know a shared secret to doesn't
send a message to you on the other hand
when we would use symmetric encryption
for communication then we somehow need
to exchange the key need to agree on the
common symmetric key that we used to
encrypt and decrypt the messages so so
this this is the the biggest
disadvantage of symmetric encryption
that the key needs to be somehow shared
and I just cannot send the key via via a
normal communication channel because
that would be equivalent of sending the
message because if I send the key in
like in plain text everyone cam is able
to see the key and then they can use it
to decrypt the message so with a
symmetric encryption this is not a
problem however there is a pitfall
usually a symmetric encryption czar much
much much slower than the symmetric ones
so so there is always a trade-off
weather which encryption to use in in
software engineering we use symmetric
encryption any everywhere where it's
possible and using a symmetric
encryptions only on the on that part
where where it really matters
to have public kids or we need key
exchange usually asymmetric encryption
must be used only for key key agreement
and key exchange for symmetric
encryption and no real-world application
uses a symmetric encryption for for
actual data or message encryption so
what are some of the different types of
symmetric and asymmetric encryption
usually there are a lot of algorithms
during the history of cryptography they
were inventing a lot of algorithms we
can talk about stream ciphers and block
ciphers maybe just some of the more
commonly used ones
all right the most commonly used
nowadays is AES which is a symmetric
encryption and the on the a symmetric
part there is RSA which is the most most
well-known one and the different
elliptic curve algorithms are are also
getting popular because they are
generally faster than than RSA and they
have led smaller key sizes so yeah
Triple DES or Triple DES a yes rc4 these
are these symmetric algorithms can
quickly tell and RSA and yeah curve 25
by 1/9 is the is an isometric for
example or DSA so there are several ours
have you got some examples where these
are used with the different algorithms
used I'm aware that most of the disk
encryption tools that that's either
built in the operating systems or or can
be used differently for example the
Microsoft speed Locker or the looks
encryption in Linux or the veracrypt
application so they are using AES
encryption for for this concretion
the secure web itself it's using most of
the time it is using using AES with 120
4-bit keys for example and in the same
secure web so the HTTPS is also using
NSA and diffie-hellman key agreement for
key exchange so for example in in in web
insecure web communications both type of
encryption is used yes actually the FF
age secure shell is also using both
encryptions they are they usually both
HTTP and SS ages is they are supporting
different set of algorithms and and the
the server and the client can agree on
the beginning which ones to use and and
they usually support all that I
mentioned what types of systems can we
apply in twinned encryption to usually
the trivial answer would be where two
parties there are two ends into the
communication but there are a lot of lot
of examples we can use end to end
encryption like text messaging voice
calls video cos Phi storage for example
and and it man these these are maybe the
main ones I'm aware of what types of
systems should we apply in doing
encryption to that's an easy one oh yeah
actually this yeah we believe that that
that the most systems use end-to-end
encryption is is the best for for for
privacy and keeping keeping people's
privacy the way it is private so I'm
we're gonna discuss instant messaging
voice in email scenarios I briefly and
then move into into service
communication scenarios so in the
instant messaging our scenario we have
we apply in doing encryption to instant
messaging some of these offerings are
signal wire facebook messenger if you
opt into it whatsapp telegram viber
iMessage what are your thoughts re on
these offerings
in the ethics I'm pretty glad that you
have a lot of text messaging services
and I also like that the most of these
services are built on the on the same
protocol which is which was developed by
open whisper systems it is the signup
protocol and it's a pretty well design
protocol to use it and yeah actually the
difference is originating from these
between these providers that they are
making decisions whether making the
encryption the end-to-end encryption a
default one or or or just an opt-in
feature whether how how directly they
are communicating the the cryptographic
operations that's happening in behind
and this these factors can can be
affecting how people are using this
these services how easy they are to use
and the a DDD level of security as well
so regardless of fusing the same
protocol and the same messaging
implementation under the hood there are
also some differences and which affects
the security yeah I'm just thinking um a
lot with signal so like the actual
algorithm is free and open source and
they they retain your phone number and
last login date but nothing else there's
no other metadata that they retain in
the likes of wire is open source it's
yes it's its headquarters are in
Switzerland and it's got a you servers
which I think is there's quite a big
plus because the because the
governmental restrictions around who can
access your data and that sort of thing
in Switzerland a very strict and they
use the Proteas algorithm I think which
which was an implementation of the exile
Lahti protocol I forget exactly how you
say it but it was a later a night I will
be named to the double ratchet algorithm
which is I guess
signals based on and then you've got
like Facebook's messenger which is yeah
of course optin and uses the signal
protocol but it clicks a lot of metadata
from users and then you I like with your
whatsapp again it uses a signal protocol
but clicks a conversation and a lot of
other metadata and it's owned by
Facebook and and and the users data goes
to Facebook so this yeah I mean these
things like that some yeah there's
actually quite a bit to way up there all
right
yes actually that's that's that's the
toughest part of it from the users
perspective I think that even if we we
we would like to do to keep our privacy
and we are trying to keep to having an
open eye on on secure solutions and try
to try to use the most secure one
actually in these days the user has to
be really careful and and and and aware
of what services they are using and how
actually they are working what what
information what metadata these services
are are collecting so so yeah this is a
hard hard question on the on the open
source topic I think it's really great
to have have these these underlying
protocols as an open source because then
it gives even developers or security
researchers an opportunity to review and
and see whether actually what's
implemented in in the library in the
protocol is implemented well because
it's really easy to use the cryptography
in a wrong way so it's it turns out that
it does not protect at all but but yeah
even if even if someone builds on on the
same library on the same protocol it's
still you can you can make wrong
decisions decisions and use it use it
wrongly yeah yeah I'm just thinking
about likes of Facebook
whatsit telegram in viber they're
basically using encryption as a
marketing thing basically to pull people
to use the application but they're still
collecting loads of metadata on their
users and in passing it on to other
entities and that sort of thing as well
so I'm the likes of telegram and there's
been controversies around are there
hand-rolled MT protocol protocol and
again they store lots of metadata the
viber has got a hand-rolled closed
source signal protocol then there's
iMessage which is the iOS offering which
is in green encrypted it's closed source
so I guess it comes down to whether you
want to you know whether you can trust
our iOS
I mean it's possibly a backdoor in there
mm-hmm yeah actually yeah if you if you
are using closed source solutions then
you have to have trust in the service
provider and yeah at some point you you
have to trust in something but yeah the
more more thing you you'll you see the
more thing the to you you are able to to
check and and look through then yeah the
last thing you have to worry about but
for example that's seen through I find
it interesting that if you are using
end-to-end encryption and just
reflecting 12 our first topic now it
means that if you use end-to-end
encryption for example then you don't
have to trust the cloud or the service
provider because it's because it doesn't
matter whether they are saying that they
they won't touch your day town they
store it and cryptid or they use secure
transport channels because it's from the
point that you'll start using end-to-end
encryption it's it's it doesn't matter
any anymore because the messages are
protected either way from the from the
origin from when they originating to all
the way to the to the target so that's
an interesting topic that you are
gaining you are you you have to trust
the the encryption
and the end-to-end encrypted service
itself but you don't have to trust the
the des network provider and don't have
to trust the this service provider or
the cloud provider so that's that's an
interesting topic yeah the other issue
is like the meter data right yeah yeah
the meter data is always a difficult
question usually they are documented or
at least they should be documented in in
the terms of use section or or or in the
yeah the privacy policy actually there
the now that gdpr is coming in the indy
you the lot of restrictions and there
are more things then these companies
have to document well where there are
data and metadata going what they are
they doing with it so so it's getting
more visible from now and I find it a
good thing as well
yeah yes sir so what's the voice
scenario
I'm we've got offerings again signal
which is a voice and video over IP
silent circle there's an offering called
silent phone now I've got FaceTime which
is you know is offering whatsapp again
in in Skype which is pretty much known
to be spyware what are your thoughts
around these offerings in new attics
actually I'm not I'm not really familiar
with them you're not not really using it
I think using end-to-end encryption in
in in voice cause it's not not much
different than using it for for
messaging for example so the principles
are the same the only difference is that
there are more data to encrypt and and
it they have to be more performance
optimized so because video and and audio
has a lot more data to encrypt and sent
through the network so yeah my opinion
if if we trust for example I'm siege
then why wouldn't we trust face time
it's the same rider I don't see much
difference if they just depends on what
kind of data we are
encrypting can I reflect on the hand
roll the encryption party were
mentioning telegram I was reading
through the articles about telegram and
and I would like to mention that hand
roll encryption has like levels which
led on which level you are using hand
roll the encryption and yeah actually
there are the level of cryptographic
primitives the AES block cipher
encryption or the NSA standard or or or
hash functions or the these really the
real low-level operations and yet the
rule of thumb is always that you don't
implement your own cryptography and for
example in case of telegram they are
they are using well-known primitives so
they are don't use hand rolling cream
and hand rolling encryption and the next
level is how how you put these together
to create a service or create a protocol
for example and yeah you can you can
make mistakes here and at any point and
again if you have some well-known
protocol to use then then yeah you
should use that you should stick with
that because they have they have proved
they are proven that then they oak then
they are okay for example if you would
like to authenticate users with password
you are using the SRP protocol which is
designed for that but yeah not to
mention that this protocol has now the
sixth version because the first five was
was not so perfect so even the standard
I'll done the dies protocols have flaws
and yeah but if you are if you are
dealing with the video field where there
is no proven protocol then you can and
it's not if you do it right it's I don't
think it's they are not much vulnerable
if they are doing it right so putting
retargeting cryptographic primitives
together to form a protocol or create an
application if done well it's
can be told that it's hand-rolled but
but it's hand rolled on a different
level so it's not on the cryptographic
levels which are which are well known we
at Treasure eight we also have parts in
our protocols that that would be called
hand rolled in in this term but we don't
think we don't count it as hand rod
cryptography we also use standard
algorithms we use standard protocols
where we can yeah so it's more about the
night of our low level ones so so moving
into the email scenario an email is not
in doing encrypted in this we're using
GPG your PGP which is a pain tearless
provides encryption to the server start
TLS I can provide encryption between the
servers Google made various
announcements from late 2013 through to
about March 2014 they now provide not
only mandatory TLS encryption between
clients in their servers but also
between their own data centers now this
is good but it's not necessarily in
tween encryption so this transitional
seems between each server between each
server when the data goes now from
resting to in transit and vice versa the
NSA in and GCHQ I'm more than likely
here backdoors into their servers as
well so I think it's safe to say if we
want email or any cloud privacy for that
matter we need to take the
responsibility ourselves is there any
hope here now how can we improve the
email situation yeah actually the
problem arises from the fact that yeah
email was was created way before then
when when the the encryption was was was
a necessity back in the days of the
internet rising so so yeah there are a
lot of solutions already it's not just
PGP but there is a s/mime which is not
well known but it's also standard
protocol its emblem implemented a lot of
me
client applications as well which is
also using a symmetric encryption and
and certificates like like PGP dude so
the the it is similar to that and yeah
in during the in the times in the last
ten or twenty years computer engineers
tried to make email secure but yeah
having having a TLS channel or secure
channel when we are transmitting email
so when I transmit my email to the to my
email provider to my SMTP server than
they are trans they are transferring it
all over the de network you have to know
that that your email is like hoping
around
tens of levels before it reaches the the
final destination and yeah nothing
nothing em forces it to have all the
hopes all these steps being encrypted
between all the servers so so that can
be any part of the of the transmitter
where your email will be transmitted
without encryption and yeah that's the
that's the flow of the protocol and I
really appreciate Google who was a
pioneer in yeah in in making start TLS
and and and and TLS in in email
communication mandatory it is great but
but it it doesn't make it end to end
encryption in in the sand in the sense
that we were talking about in in the
beginning of the of our conversation
so being it being the email encrypted in
transit does not mean that it's not
accessible to the to the email servers
or or the the email providers during
during transit or at these points where
it's just switching direction so they
had the real solution here is PGP or
s/mime but but they are really hard to
use for
for an average user it's true that they
are not easy to use and and there are a
lot of you know initiatives to make
email secure there are some some secure
email providers who try to make it make
it easier like protonmail for example if
you are communicating between two
protonmail use users via email then you
get encrypted email automatically
without any kind of setup or hassle
which is great the same applies for
tooten Alta for example so so there is
hope I'm so there are a lot of providers
who try to fill this gap to make email
secure without the hassle of setting up
EGP keys and and all the that stuff that
makes it makes it complicated for an
average user yeah so we just kind of
move into the industry's communication
I'm scenarios now his software engineers
were building complex and distributed
systems to run on servers we know very
little about aka the cloud this is this
is untrusted territory now why do we
need encryption between these components
usually can you be can you be a bit more
specific or do you have some some
examples I can reflect them would be
easier to answer yeah so so as I say
you're an organization you're developing
basically any sort of a system in the
cloud and you've got a bunch of micro
services and they're all talking to each
other so so why do we need into any
encryption between those micro services
and I guess the end user mm-hmm actually
that there is is that it is the same
principle to be sure it is the same
principle that I was already talking
about so they don't have to have to
trust their own cloud provider if you
don't don't depend on on the cloud
platform
encryption but but do it on your own and
if you do it on your own you can do it
in an end-to-end encrypted way or you
will actually end up doing it in and to
end encrypted way then you are not
depending on on the cloud provider or
you don't have to check the news whether
they are already being hacked or some
flow is is discovered because the
communication with between your software
components whether they are being the
for example micro-services or different
micro services or or or a service and
the end-user application the users
device you don't need to configure and
and monitored and be aware of the cloud
providers encryption solution and yeah
it and then depends on the level of
security would you would like to achieve
or the the level of of encryption the
level of protection the the data you are
communicating so if you are if you are
dealing with let's say medical some
medical devices that that constantly
sends medical information for example
heart rate or blood sugar levels to to a
cloud service then it's actually
considered personal information and you
have you have obligations to protect
them much protect them better and for in
this scenario you you cannot do anything
else but let's use end-to-end encryption
because that's the that's the only only
way you can achieve that that level of
security then you can be sure that even
if in the very very unlikely scenario
whether your cloud provider gets gets
hacked or there is some malicious
employee who at the cloud provider who
tries to dump all the in-form
or or just tries to steal a hard-disk
they they won't won't have access to any
critical information or at any private
or personal or health health care
records so that's how you can for
example adhere to the law in this terms
yeah so secure and data wrists and in
transit is generally a solved problem
but securing data and uses harder if we
can achieve this then we can achieve
into an encryption if we have to decrypt
in order to process then we've got a
scene and this is generally where
attackers will focus their efforts so
rather than creating a same earlier in
tween encryption by decrypting to
perform processing at least look at some
techniques for securing data and news so
this is providing into an encryption so
I've got I've got a selection here we're
just going to walk through I've got a
full memory encryption cpu-based key
storage and claves and cryptographic
protocols so let's sum start with a full
memory encryption so the system provides
both confidentially confidentiality and
integrity predictions of code and data
which are encrypted everywhere outside
the CPU boundary can you explain how
this works and how software engineers
can take advantage of oh yeah like
disclaimer that I'm not I'm really
expert on these I'm aware though I'm
aware of basically what they are doing
but I try to do my best so I like to
start with full memory encryption it
means that usually we like in computer
the computer engineers think that the
level of protection is is the the
boundary of the of the hardware or the
boundary of the computer so if we I have
my laptop in front of me that's the
level of protection that we need to
focus on so whether my lab laptop is
still on or not
but we don't take into consideration
when we are designing software or
hardware that they will someone just
comes and takes out memory of the the
memory module of my of my laptop but in
the cloud for example it's it's a bit
different because there is a lot of
hardware next to each other and and
software are using the same hardware we
utilized on on the same environment so
so there's more need to protect each
each from from other and and from any
kind of flows I'm just thinking about
the raw hemorrhage tech I think was
called the raw hammer attack with a
recent research is uncovered that the
attackers were able to actually get a
exists in the memory are sitting right
beside I want beside another row yeah
and yeah that's that's an example for
example and what full memory encryption
does is that also encrypts the memory
the operational memory of the computer
and the encryption is done in this by
the CPU itself and and it happens
transparently so different parts of the
memory are encrypted with different keys
and the different keys belong to
different software this is quite a new
new advanced advanced in CPU design
actually to be honest I I find it more
like a marketing invention or or for for
for marketing recent events shows that
that if there is a there is a flow in
the indc pio design it doesn't really
matter what what protections the CPU is
offering how many layers of encryption
you are you are putting to your memory
if there is a there is a flow in the CPU
design then the attackers will just
focus on that and if you have a flow in
your CPU then you will be able to
recover the encryption key for them for
the memory so it doesn't really matter
whether you encrypt the memory or not so
it's very limited scenarios where we're
full memory encryption can help usually
normal CPU normal protections built in
the CPU will a clear memory
virtualization and and and protection
bits should be enough to protect
different probe programs from each other
or different visualized operating
systems from each other full memory
encryption is just an addition and an
additional layer which I don't think it
has much more use but yeah so what do
you think about cpu-based key storage so
this is where a kernel patch provides
CPU only base encryption to defend
against the likes of cold boot attacks
I'm allowing RAM to be treated as
untrusted can you tell us a bit about
this and where the software engineers
could be and should be able to use this
in the systems where constructing this
actually also I also find that very
limited use use of this this is usually
used for like bootstrapping problems
when when you when you have someone
somehow have to provide the secure
environment from the beginning it's like
the similar similar concept to secure
boot for example so you somehow the
operating system has to start and and
you have to get into a state where you
value well you can be sure that no one
was able to to change the code or change
the change the environment before you
start the the real operation so so yeah
CPU key beast key storage because in in
in the CPU there's very limited space
for four keys and and and operations
there is also like a smaller set of data
that that can be encrypted and decrypted
and usual days are just keys stages
where you can just use these keys to
decrypt and validate the other parts of
the software which in turn will be
loaded into memory yeah in in some
really security critical parts or for
example when you have to design security
modules for example or the smart cards
or something like that it's it can be a
useful solution so you don't have to
expose your your data to to the database
sort into the memory but again I I find
it a limited scope so it's not a general
solution you can apply alright okay so
so let's you look at any claves so we
touched on Intel software got extensions
ECX and the show on docker security that
was show number 290 darwin in places and
i cryptid and Rambo like clear text
within the CPU in its case until induced
this concept of enclave's as part of
their SGX providing a set of new ECX
enabled CPU instructions
18 of the mind allowing user level code
to allocate private regions of known
sorry probe regions of memory known as
enclave's intel has this concept of of
of symmetrical provisioning key which
resides in both the east ixnay would
chip in on the Intel servers so to
establish an enclave the software needs
to offer its provisioning key to Intel
and if there's a match and their
database and tower will issue an
attestation key that let's set up the
enslaves so is Jax has been heavily
criticized by security researchers some
of them our MIT Victor Causton and swin
of us
Devadas so as far as I can tell by using
ECX
we're just shifting the trust now from
untrusted clouds to Intel so we're
essentially just shifting where we trust
I'm with it but your take yeah exactly
actually that's that's
that's does does the same debate for
example again I'm just I can refer to to
secure boot which also had this
controversy when it was was initiated by
by Microsoft back then that okay they
are secure boot is great that if they
are controlling the key then what's the
use but yeah but it's not black and
white
I find secure enclaves as cheeks an
interesting concept and I find a lot of
uses and yeah I'm working in the cloud
industry and and especially in the cloud
industry that's that's that's a promise
promising solutions solution to two
trusted computing problem but they're
the same the scenario you were
mentioning that that somehow you have to
process the data but in a way that this
is not not accessible to this Suns the
service provider because yeah if you
decrypt the data then it's it's all it's
already exposed but if somehow you
managed to to keep it private then then
you can create a lot lot of operations
so so yeah now there are major cloud
providers for example Asian the they are
rolling out secure computing which is
based on Intel SGX and yeah while it
being a relatively new concept like it's
it's introduced four years ago three
years ago and in in the security world
and cryptography world it's it's not
that not a long time to make it major
and yeah definitely actually it has
faults but I think they have a lot of a
lot of promising concepts and yeah in
the cloud it's it's it be good that I
will be able to deploy an application
which which operates on private data in
a way that I don't have to be cautious
whether my data is accessible
to the cloud provider however it brings
up another problem which is how my code
how the data is it's getting to the end
clave so so it's always always a boost
there is always a bootstrapping problem
it's it with with end to end encryption
okay you have interaction but somehow
you have to manage the keys that you
have to exchange the keys so on the
other party will be able to decrypt so
that's the that's the the problem
you engineers have to solve Intel has an
has an option for that which is remote
attestation which is again involves
registering at Intel and and and yeah
there is there is some controversy
around this yeah I hope for hope that
they somehow we open up this platform
more and and then I think it will be
usable
I think the are these chicks patents
disclosed pretty much in no uncertain
terms that the launch in clave was
introduced to ensure that each enclave's
author has a business relationship with
Intel and implements a software
licensing system so so basically we're
just shifting our trust a to Intel yeah
the same happened a few years ago when
intervie TD was was introduced it is the
same same issue yeah it seems like Intel
is like this kind of solutions whether
they have a key or a backdoor like
access to our devices I hope there are a
lot of other CPU vendors so well you see
I hope hope for the best
so just moving on to to cryptographic
protocols so I've got secured a
multi-party computation in homomorphic
encryption so I'm with with secure
multi-party the computation also known
as
secure computation or privacy-preserving
computation the idea here is to create
methods for parties to jointly compute a
function over the inputs while keeping
those inputs private and then with
homomorphic encryption now this allows
us to perform computations on ciphertext
the result being the result of the
operations as though they had been
performed on plaintext but still
encrypted can you explain a bit about
secure multi-party computation in
homomorphic encryption and how they
differ actually it works it works in a
way that that you described again I'm
not a great expert on this but they are
really really really interesting and and
more like in a crypto nerd way
interesting as far as I know what they
are still in in academic research phase
as as I know they are they are too slow
currently to to be to make it usable in
any kind of real world applications but
yeah they are they work in a way that
you have an encrypted data and it's
encrypted in a special way
which allows certain operations to be to
be performed on the encrypted data and
then you get back an encrypted result
which which is then if you decrypt it
you get the actual result of the weather
if you perform the operation the
decrypted data but you don't have to
decrypt it and the promise here is that
if you are able to to perform operations
on on unencrypted data then you will you
can upload a lot of computations from
the client side to the to the server
side while you don't have to give up the
the encryption and don't don't have to
give up the the privacy
yeah there is an example which is which
is like feasible right now which is
which is encrypted searching however it
needs so we are you you are
using bloom filters for example you are
able to do a search on a data that you
don't know and you don't know the search
term actually which because it is
encrypted or not it's converted in a way
that you cannot get the original search
term back and you have a lot of you have
a huge index of the information then you
can perform limited search for example
an encrypted data and you will get which
encrypted part contains the data you are
looking for but but this is also costly
the terms that you have to maintain a
lot of indexes and and and huge index
databases so there are some researches
but but unfortunately they are they are
still in interface that they are not not
fast enough to use in improving
production so yeah you saw the indexes
are indexes of hashes are they and I
just comparing hashes with ashes yeah
that's that's a really yeah that's a
really basic example but that that you
know that's just for looking for an
exact match but searching is a bit
different and you have to you can you
would like to look you look for sub
strings and you you have to look that
you would like to look for like a word
in a 100 page document and you would
like to find that so so yeah a hash
matching is is is one special case of
encrypted search but yeah all right so
it sounds like it's not ready for prime
time yet yeah so so now that we've
talked a little bit about securing data
in use what are some of the best options
for software engineers today to perform
processing on encrypted data well are
there any not really so what you can do
is decrypt it and then do the operation
and then encrypt it again which makes
for in the end-to-end encrypted example
so if you are using end-to-end
encryption it makes it
really difficult this is for example a
problem we are facing that that all
operations have to be done on client
side so like these data transformations
on migrations or or or anything like
that has to be performed the client side
so we have somehow have to wait for or
ask the user to login to and to the to
his device or his client for example and
it makes it really really a challenge to
to to implement changes and protocols
because if you rely when your users to
to use their clients and they won't they
there will be always a lot of users who
are not using they are travelling around
the world or just simply stopped using
the app the application and then you are
stuck with with a lot of data that is
not that you cannot migrate and you have
to support all protocols and the world
your all standards for for ages so it's
a really difficult part if you if you
choose end to end encryption and you
don't control both ends of the
encryption if you have controls for
example if you have like the micro
services the example and you have two or
three micro services communication then
of course it's not a problem because you
control both parties but if like you we
have a user involved it's getting
difficult so I'm just transitioning now
from into Indian ssin to encryption
between points of communication so we
touched on what CSPs are doing to
encrypt outcomes between data centers
and services and components and the
cloud security show that is with scott
piper i show number 314 so basically
came the and we don't really know what
are they are doing so it's up to the
developer and we can set up mutual tes
authentication between our components
mutual tailors authentication is not
yeah if it adds a layer of of security
to the communication because not just a
single part of the of the single party
single peer of the communication is
authenticated but also the other peer so
you can if you use mutual authentication
you can be sure that really no one
intercepts your your traffic between
your your your services usually combine
it with depending on the the
architecture you so if for example if
you are if you are depending on virtual
machines for example so it combining
with with disk encryption and and and
secure communication actually you are
creating a closed-loop where where
information cannot really go out you can
also set up if you have a a cloud
application for example and which is
distributed in different data centers
around the around the world then you can
set up secure VPN connections between
your data centers and then you are
creating a whole private network of
between your computers or between your
services which is also adds security
with your application and yeah and there
are different ways you can communicate
via your storage for example if you use
encryption before sending the data to
the storage and the other service is
using the storage is an input then you
also created the secured communication
channel between your services for
example other than that I'm suddenly I
cannot tell I'm aware of other solution
these are the traditional solutions and
the solutions that are used in practice
in the cloud normal days so communicate
secure communication which is actually
usually it's it's a basic thing to have
and VPN communications encrypted storage
so just moving on to libraries ciphers
and tools so there's a huge amount of
poor advice that are I think pretty much
most of us aware that are on the
internet on the likes of Stack Overflow
on it sort of thing now let's get some
solid advice for our engineers what
ciphers and modes should we be avoiding
in which should we be using for which
purpose that's yeah that's that's an
added some more complicated question
that it seems because it really depends
on on what what you are using the the
encryption for for example if you have
if you are developing an application for
for government or military for example
then you will end up with a with a lot
of standards like F VPS or Common
Criteria and and things like that that
makes a specific cypher and a specific
mode mandatory for example but that but
that's an extreme example general is
saying if we stick with modes so let's
say a es and the different modes of of
how a es can be used generally speaking
ECB electronic codebook mode it's it's
really hard to use properly so if you
don't really know what to do don't use
it it's that can be that can be a real
off dump but that's that that's where it
actually ends because the other modes
are usually play well in terms of
security but but all of them can be can
be can be used improperly for example if
you if you are planning to develop a
disk encryption or block encryption
software you you will end up using XDR
mode
the one of the newest modes and
especially designed for for this
concretion CBC or cfb are the the the
general way to go so these are the
traditional modes they are using but for
example for CBC there is the padding
Oracle attack which should be avoided
with message authentication so it's
there's all the modes has has some some
points where and then it can they can go
wrong
GCM for example I would I would suggest
GCM because it's not just it's actually
easy to use and it also has message
integrity built in so it will be faster
for example and also get you get message
integrity you don't have to use a
message authentication code in addition
to encryption to provide integrity
encryption itself is not it's never
enough you have to provide integrity and
GCM does it in one step for example so
yeah yeah so so I can be hard for
software engineers to know which ciphers
and KT ifs I should use a KD of sparing
key derivation functions and what do we
need to look for in a library yeah
that's that's that's more and that's
that's an easier question I would go I
think the most the most important thing
that the library should be maintained so
that's one of the one of the first thing
that if we for example a treasure it we
choose the library sort what the library
we see whether it is it actively
maintained or not having a library that
is not touched like for two years and it
seems like it's okay but at the point
when you find some bugs or flows or
something turns out then having a quick
fix is can be essential for you so so
active maintenance is is a key point
of course if you can find find some
informations regarding whether is it is
it was it reviewed by by a security
expert or an organization does it have
any certifications or or public reviews
how many other softwares are using it so
they are just which is good if you don't
have if they if the library doesn't have
any kind of certifications or or
security audits then the number of users
can be a good heuristic whether is it
good or not but it's not Nadja it's not
generally applicable so there may be for
example open SSL three or four years ago
it was everyone was using open SSL and
it turned out that hardly it was
affecting almost 90% of the Internet so
it's not always the case but it's a good
heuristic and yeah for example if you
are developing and closed source or an
open source software you also have to
check for the license as well so and
these are the factors what it what about
some how important is that essentially
created by cryptographers yeah that's
yeah that's always a good sign if you if
some of the editors or contributors are
well-known cryptographer yeah so I'm
just got a Krishna man I'm at Reiser
nan convergent crypto so Twitter uses
non convergent crypto to store I uses
data can you talk a little bit about
this in our what it means yeah I would
invert the question so what does
convergent crypto means it means that if
you are encrypting the same data then
you will usually or end up with with the
same ciphertext so so for example if
there are several users who are
uploading
one gigabyte video there was an there
was this birthday party and everyone is
just uploading the video of it and the
same video is uploaded by several people
then it's it can be used to to
deduplicate on the server side so they
the encrypted content will be the same
if the the same file exact same file is
uploaded then the encrypted form will be
the same so you don't have to upload it
again most of the cloud storage
providers used it as a form of
deduplication and it's actually not a
bad thing so it's not another thing to
avoid in any any cost but it means that
so let's see there is a there is a
warrant for example from a government
organization so they would like to know
what a user is storing in there at their
storage provider and the storage for
either in case of convergent
cryptography the search profit cannot
tell what the user is storing but if the
government gives you a file let's see
whether this file is uploaded let it be
some illegal content for example then
the storage provider can tell whether
this illegal content is in the user
storage because the same content will be
will be resulting in the same encryption
so it can be used to prove whether the
whether a given content is is is in the
possession of a user in case of
non-covered conversion crypto this is
not the case because every time a file
is uploaded a new key a new IV is
generated and then then it means that
the resulting ciphertext will be
different each time so this kind of
claims are not not feasible so we cannot
tell if someone gives us a file let's
see whether this is this file exists in
any of our users we cannot tell it
because the same file will always result
in different different results different
cryptid forms it's these sorts of things
that pretty much won me over - actually
I'm Gareth treszura along with the likes
of wizards bug bounty which I think had
something like a thousand hackers
hacking on booze everyone yes yes yes we
offered $5,000 $50,000 sorry
the ones who who may be able to to break
our encryption and actually we've
weakened the encryption so at resurrect
we have two levels at least two levels
of security so there is the end-to-end
encryption and then the plus the
traditional security layers like secure
communication channel TLS and and server
side authentication and and all the
traditional stuff and the last party we
were opened so only the the the
end-to-end encryption part has to be a
hacked and yeah fortunately they were
not able to to manage to hack it but you
have to be honest that was that we were
expecting yeah it's a pretty good
testament um we're gonna have to wrap up
so thanks for joining us today it's been
a really educational and fun Peter yeah
thanks for the opportunity as for
software engineering radio others was
Kim Carter thanks for listening the se
radio an educational program brought to
you by Archer police software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of se radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening